my career in side projects and open
source basically this is so i've been
knocking around with um uh side projects
and open source things that
20 years now it turns out and i realized
recently that
every key moment in my career started
out as a side project
um so i've got a great track record of
turning side projects into opportunities
um but the next thing i want to do is
turn that my current major
open source side project into something
that's sustainable without me having to
go and
work for somebody else um or start
another company i'll probably start
another company but we'll see
so um i'm going to show you a bunch of
side projects i've worked on over the
years
and uh talk through how they in how they
um
how they sort of influenced where i
ended up going um
so my first side project of note was a
site that i launched in 1999
um this was an online gaming site i was
a keen player of team fortress classic
and i was in a clan
and i was trying to run a league and all
of that kind of stuff and um this was
i don't know if blogs were even a thing
in 1999 this was i considered this a
news website it was news about the game
and um
i had to this is the aesthetic of this i
think is very
online gaming in the late 90s i'm quite
proud of that um
but this was a project that i span up to
start building a community around this
game that i was playing
and um i started i started running this
this league for clans to compete and
that got me my first job in in
technology i ended up taking two years
before university
moved to london to work for this company
called what and gameplay
which was for a brief moment the darling
of the 1999 um
like london technology industry it
raised 88 million pounds and then lost
all of it
um like in the dot-com crash it was
quite spectacular
i think at one point um we were selling
games online like the past
what's that
i think we just had some um background
noise but we're meeting
yeah i think that that that the share
price was like
uh two pound 21 when we when we actually
when we
ipo'd and then three and a half pence
two years later when the company pretty
much collapsed um so i got to see the
first.com boom up close which was really
exciting
um but yeah and that that so that came
out from the sort of
my first foray into into online news and
such like um
luckily for me i hadn't gone to
university yet so when the entire.com
industry
crashed i could go and shelter in
academia for
a few years and get my degree um so
after that i spent a um this blogs were
now a thing so i started a blog
um nearly 20 years ago wow and this was
back when
there were only about 100 people who
were blogging about web development so
we all knew each other which was really
exciting um because
uh chap i knew called adrian hulivarti
was a journalist
web um developer in kansas and he posted
a job job opportunity he said hey
we're building local news websites in
kansas we've got a job opening and then
this
coincides with my british my university
in england giving me the opportunity to
have a year in industry so you can find
a job somewhere
um if it's abroad you can get a student
visa which is crucially useful
and you can go out spend a year in year
in industry and then come back and
finish your degree
so i ended up moving out to kansas from
from um from bath in england this was my
first proper experience of the united
states
um this tiny little town called lawrence
kansas population i think
like less than a hundred thousand people
um
to work for a newspaper called the
lawrence journal world and this was an
extraordinary job again it sort of came
out of this
my side project of just blogging about
stuff
um it was extraordinary because while it
was a tiny newspaper it was really well
funded
and um the goal was always to punch so
far
above our weight that nobody could
believe that we were a tiny little
newspaper
to um take a little local newspaper and
my favorite example
um in i'm sure as americans
probably i imagine most people in this
call understand american culture better
than i do
americans are really into their kids
baseball and softball
so there was this softball league in the
town and our boss a guy called rob
curley said we're going to treat these
kids softball teams like they're the new
york yankees we're going to do
photos and team bios and schedules i'm
going to let the parents sign up for sms
messages whenever their
their kids scores a whatever you score
in softball a
run um and uh we we sent in turns out
and we took 360 degree photographs
of every softball court in town to put
up on the website this was in what 2002
2002 now 2003 um so it's quicktime vr i
think we were using for this
so absolutely absurd levels
of of over-the-top interest in this
kid's softball stuff
um and because we had this culture of
trying to punch way above our weight
adrian and i had been experimenting with
new ways of building websites um we
wanted to use python um
we'd both been using php and so we ended
up building
out this system for building websites um
like the kids softball thing we had to
put together we had a three-day deadline
to put that together
and then shortly after i left the
newspaper we open-sourced it and that
was um this is django the django web
framework
which was born in a local newspaper at a
local newspaper in lawrence kansas
and today it's used by instagram and um
discus and all sorts of different places
so this
as an open source project has been
incredibly influential i have got the
the chart of interest over time from um
i think that's from google trends
oops why did that happen um
and again that this this came out this
came out of us working in a newsroom
environment and needing to turn around
relatively complex relational database
websites in
very very short amounts of time on
journalism deadlines because the fun
thing about working on news stuff
is that you know if it takes you three
months to build an application to
support a story there's no point in
building it at all
you have to be able to to publish things
at the rate of the news cycle
um so based on all of that uh i ended up
back in england working at the
guardian and so the guardian is one of
the uk's leading newspapers
um they had they this was around 2010
and they were coming off a three-year
horrifying giant content management
system like enterprise rebuild
so they were all relative kind of burned
out and looking to
try and start doing more of this sort of
agile um
very quick turnaround like data data
journalism reporting stuff
so i came in to to start doing those
kinds of things and i got to work on
some really fun projects there um
there was a actually well this was one
of the first wikileaks
story this was back in 2008 and
wikileaks got their hands
on the membership list of the bnp the
the the far right um party in in the uk
and it had 18 000 names on it and the
guardian is not the kind of newspaper
that publishes 18 000 people's names for
for being members of the political party
so the question was
how can we what is a responsible way of
using this data that doesn't like
you know um affect anyone's personal
privacy so what we ended up doing was
some
um was geocoding people's dresses to
parliamentary constituencies
so that we could generate a heat map of
where the bnp had the most mem
and had the most party members in um
in the uk and this this was one of my
first projects of the guardian the
really exciting thing about it is that
it got printed in the newspaper
because i built this um i built this
using svg um
and the great thing about svg is that
it's it's vector quality and you can
export it to illustrator and put it out
so
i've still got like five copies of this
newspaper on the shelf behind me i think
um but this also this ties into this
idea of side projects because
one of the things i span out of this was
a sort of internal project
side project for the guardian which was
a self-service tool
where reporters could like uh
upload a a list of parliamentary
constituencies and numbers
and get back one of these svg heat maps
so the idea was to
um and it was we i i built that at one
of the guardians internal hack days
um the problem i found is that um a
bunch of journalists started using this
thing which i'd knocked together in my
sort of spare work time
and um after i left the guardian a
couple of years after i left
um i met up with somebody who had worked
with them he said yes you know you're um
you left that thing running on your
desktop computer and your desk and so we
had to leave your desktop turned on for
six months
and then we had to figure out how to
virtualize it and stick it in our data
and in vmware and data center somewhere
and um
yeah next time next time how about
writing some deployment instructions
and so from that i learned that um
you can cause certain amounts of um of
chaos with with these projects if you
don't
don't assume that they're going to run
for a lot longer than you thought they
were going to run for
and i've become very interested
interested since then in
documenting things but also making sure
that
companies have really good mechanisms
for internal deployments of these kinds
of projects so it doesn't end up running
on someone's desktop um
under a desk somewhere um but the most
fun project to work with guardian was
another thing again something that
started as a
a commute side project i had a two-hour
train ride into work which was
just enough time to knock together
prototypes of things
um and that was this tool for
investigating your
member of parliament's expense claims um
there was a
ongoing freedom of information campaign
to try and get the expense documents
from our
our representatives and when they
finally came out
um we had 450 000 pages of documents
that we needed to go through
so we decided to try and do it with
crowdsourcing we put these all up on the
website
and we gave people a button to start
reviewing random pages of mp's expenses
so here's page 34 of janet dean's
incidental expenses provision and we'd
ask our users to glance
over it and click a button to say if
they thought it looked interesting
should a journalism go journalists go
and look at that kind of stuff
um and interestingly with this project
the most
important detail the thing that really
helped to get working is that we stuck
the mp's official
mug shots that the their photographs on
the pages
because they all look very smug and
they're grilling in this and
it made people really angry people like
you're grinning at me
and i'm looking i'm going to dive
through your expenses and i'm gonna find
something
on you and so we had like progress
bars and we had a um a uh a scoreboard
we gamified it a bit so who who's
reviewed the most expenses
who's the person who's who's been going
after um how i well frances the most and
so on
um but it was really fun and um again it
was
the one of the ideas that the the one of
the things that really
um sort of that that this really
emphasized for me is the power of
prototyping like if you can get a
prototype
up and running in front of people in a
really short space of time
it's so much more valuable than just
talking about an idea for something
like most people myself included ideas
will sort of bat around for hours but if
you give me something concrete even if
it's a very shonky
like demo as long as it works and i can
see it it focuses the conversation
and that's a trick i've used throughout
my entire career my my first
my first resort for almost any problem
is can i build some
kind of prototype so i can get
conversations going about what's
actually feasible to do with this thing
but let's talk about side projects again
this is one of my all-time favorite
side projects um from my friend from the
past
um this is a site called wildlife near
you and the origin story of this
is a bunch of nerdy friends of
friends in england got together and we
said you know what would be really fun
let's rent a fortress for a week
and go and build stuff together like
let's have a week-long
like hackathon in some kind of fortress
because this fortress here this is
called fort
clunk it's in alderney on the channel
islands like most of the way to france
and it's napoleonic it's from the
napoleonic era
and it only costs i think about two
thousand dollars a week to rent
but it sleeps 14 people so if you divide
two thousand dollars by 14 people we're
talking like
the price of a youth hostel to stay in a
napoleonic sea fortress
with like a drawbridge and a flag and a
bugle and
it's oh my god it was the at it was it
was such a cool place
um and it actually at high tide it gets
cut off from the mainland the water
comes over the causeway
and while we were there there were
horrific storms which would crash
against the walls but you're in a castle
so it doesn't matter
so um like lightning and everything it
was it was amazing but yeah we had this
idea to
rent a fort for a week and just see if
we could build a thing together
um and so this is us on our fortress um
nerding out on things and a great thing
about fortress is they tend not to have
internet connections which is amazing
for group productivity
and so we built a website where we the
the question we were trying to answer
the crucial question is
where is my nearest llama and so the way
this worked this this
site sadly no longer exists um
wildlifenetu.com
you'd go somewhere and you'd go to a
nature reserve or a zoo
and you'd see things and you post a trip
report you'd say i went to
this the gigan farm and i saw a raven
and a buzzer in a red kite
and you'd get a profile where you had
your favorite animals and recent trips
you've taken so on but because we had
this data we could then let you
search for llamas near brighton and we
can show you that the nearest llama to
brighton is ashdown forest llama farm
um 18 miles away as reported by somebody
and this was utterly delightful um
we got pages for species here's the red
panda page that tells you your nearest
red panda
is and photographs of red pandas and
where you can see them and
all of that but then the problem we had
with this page is
we needed to show people we needed a
single photograph of red panda to
highlight
but how do we know which photograph of
the red panda is better
so we built essentially hot or not for
photographs of animals
third is you'd go here and we'd show you
two photos of
a marmot and you say well clearly the
picture on the right is a better photo
for marmot and then we'll show you two
photos of red panda
and back and forth and then we use the
album the algorithm we used for this was
the
the elo algorithm from the one that's
used in chess tournaments
and when the the film the social network
came out with mark zuckerberg about mark
zuckerberg
there's a scene in that where he's
building like hot or not for college
students
and it's the same algorithm that we
used for our best marmot photo
so i was i was told to see
that we had that element of crossover
there um
but the really fun thing we did with
world of eu
is we decided as a marketing ploy we'd
try and this was
a actually we eventually added a mobile
location button which when that
technology became available but the idea
here was it's just one question where
are you and it would show you where your
newest outlet is that was it
and um one of the highlights of my
career was when
wired magazine in the uk who had a wired
tired expired column
listed owls near you in wired and four
square and tired
so in 2010 al's near you was was hot
stuff
according to wired uk magazine um
the most important lesson i learned from
this side project
is if you're going to host something
like this don't hook up the hosting to
an
email address that you don't check on
the credit card that expires and have
backups on the same host
because i stopped paying attention for a
couple of months and
the credit card expired and the hosting
provider deleted the data and the
backups were gone
and it was really upsetting um and so a
really important lesson i
learnt from this is if you're building
side projects building side projects
that are responsible for user data where
you've got users actually trusting your
side project with their stuff
it's generally really a bad idea because
if you do that it's not a side project
it's a job
right it's you have this responsibility
that really matters
um so i took that lesson and
completely ignored it um so uh
in 2010 uh natalie dan myself got
married um
and we had a golden eagles dog wedding
which was awesome um
and then we decided that we were going
to quit our jobs and go off from
honeymoon for as long as we could get
away with so take our laptops travel
around the world try and like
earn money from freelance clients and
that kind of thing and we got as far as
morocco
um this is uh so oh i'm not sure i can't
remember where we took that photograph
actually
um and we discovered the client work was
a bit tricky because you have unreliable
internet and you know inevitably on the
day when you've got access to a good
internet connection the client hasn't
sent you the thing they said they were
going to send you
but working on side projects together
was great that's very compatible with
riding around on camels and and having
fun exploring things
um and so we started building the side
project that was
basically it was to solve a problem we
were having which was that
our friends kept on going to really cool
events and conferences and things
which we hadn't heard of and so we were
missing out um
and we ended up we had a launch party
for our side project at rick's cafe
which
actually exists in casablanca which is
very exciting um
and we released the site called
lanyard.com and lanyard was the um
the social conference directory the idea
was it's a site where
you could go to see what conferences
people you know are going to or speaking
at
and add your own conferences and
generally do that and we i remember when
we built it we were thinking you know
what
even in tech there's at least 100
conferences here there must be thousands
of conferences
in all of the industries which was
underestimating by about a factor of 100
um but the key idea was um you sign in
with twitter
we look at who you follow on twitter and
we show you events that those people
are going to or speaking at and the
speaking app bit turned out to be
crucial because
when we added conference we'd list the
speakers by their twitter ids which
meant that on the first day we launched
um there was just natalie and i working
on the site but we had over 100
profiles of users because they were
people who were speaking at conferences
that we had listed
and that meant that anyone who signed in
who followed one of these people would
get a recommendation
and speakers have a lot of followers and
so the thing went naturally viral
and within within a few days it was it
was going far
far beyond what we thought it was what
we ever expected from this this little
side project we were building
on our honeymoon um so you had
conference listings pages and profile
pages where you can see
the events that people have given given
we have vid embedded videos and slides
and all of that kind of stuff
and so this you know i said the golden
rulers don't build a side project with
user data this was a side project with
user data and it was
um taking off way way faster than we'd
ever expected
so we ended up cutting honeymoon short
and applying for y combinator
um from luxor in egypt
um i i uh we have a y combinator ask you
to send in
a um application video like a 60 second
video
ours has the has no it was as fine
wasn't it ours has a
an egyptian temple in the background
which we decided to to have there as
a sort of background thing but not
actually mentioning in the spiel that we
gave
um we got accepted into y combinator in
for the winter 2000 and
winter 2011. um what was it i can't
remember
went to 2011 um ended up cutting a
honeymoon shield moving out to mountain
view and spending three months doing the
whole
i combinator thing after which we moved
back to london
and raised money from investors and we
hired a team and we spent
three years doing the turning turning
landed into a startup
um well it was a startup trying to
figure out how to evolve it as a startup
and then in 2013 we negotiated a
um exit uh language was acquired by
eventbrite
um the entire team all six of us i think
ten including
family members moved out to um moved out
to san francisco
um and to be honest uh one of the
reasons we sold
is we had the we had to choose between
finding an acquisition
or raising a series a and when you raise
a series a
that commits you to another five to ten
years working on that project right
that's that's a
that is locking yourself into a track
and one of the questions we had to ask
ourselves was
is this the project we want to spend the
next 10 years of our life working
on and honestly we enjoyed the project
we thought it was valuable and useful
but it wasn't that
it didn't have that this is the thing we
want to dedicate ourselves to vibes so
it was um
we we found a we found a an acquisition
target that
did did well for the investors for
ourselves and for our team and
and you know i think it worked out
pretty well um
so i spent six years at eventbrite and i
got to ride the
i got to ride the um that hockey stick
from
i think it was like 150 people joined it
was over a thousand people when we left
so
in a way by getting up by selling our
startup to another company we got to
jump about five years ahead in startup
trajectory
and see what it was like to go through
that that crazy period of growth
um and remember one of the things one of
the things i discovered was the joy of
internal company side projects
um so i moved into an engineering
management role and one of the one of
the
truths of engineering management is you
can still work on code but you can never
put yourself in the critical path of
getting anything
shipped because if you do that it just
leads to terrible management and
terrible terrible contributions and it
seizes everything up
but if you want to keep your sort of
technical brain ticking over
it's great to have projects that you can
you can work on
um and so my favorite internal side
project was um
this thing here um i called it doc
search um
we really i realized that november right
we had this problem where everyone
thought our documentation was terrible
our documentation was amazing but it was
in ten different systems it was in
confluence and github wikis and um jira
tickets and um
something called this thing called
continue and the support website all of
this
google docs and all of this stuff and so
i built a side project where
basically it would run a bunch of um
scheduled crons
pull in the content from all 10
different systems stick it in a single
search index
and give you an interface over the top
and so here i can search for varnish and
it shows me
all of the documents that mention
varnish across google docs and
confluence and so on
and um great thing about side projects
like this is
nobody gets to tell you what it should
do so at one point i got a little over
excited and decided to add facet by
emoji
so you can you can so we get a list of
the emoji that show up in the different
documents and if you just want to see
the varnish documentation
that includes the rainbow emoji you can
click on that and and see it that way
um i added glossary at the top and that
kind of thing and this was part of
eventbrite's culture as well
is eventbrite as many companies do um
had hack days so a few times a year we'd
have a day where
everyone gets to drop what they're
supposed to be doing and work on a
creative project that lets them try out
new technology or experiment with ideas
they think would be interesting
and i adore hack days we did them at the
guardian um i was in
i was used to i worked a long time ago i
worked at yahoo where i was part of the
team that started the first yahoo hack
day and i feel like it's a really useful
release valve for larger companies to
to to make sure that people don't just
get burned out
and um complete and frustrated that
they're not getting to explore
outside of the projects they're working
on in the day-to-day
um but
i've come so one of the other side
projects well
a more recent side project i worked on
um was something which i think
illustrates
the ideals um the ideal
um the ideal characteristics side
project um i showed you
azneau.com earlier this website is
called owl's near me
and you can go there right now it's
housenearme.com
um natalie and i built this uh on super
super bowl sunday a few years ago
because in england everyone makes fun of
it and calls it superb
owl sunday so we figured it was a good
day to be promoting a superb
owl website and so alznemy.com
you go there you click use my location
and it shows you where your nearest owl
is
um but why it does it is it uses this
amazing website called inaturalist which
is
somebody else's crowdsource project to
gather where people have seen things
um and it's got a really good api so
owlsnewme.com
is a tiny little piece of html in
javascript it's little react app it
talks this api
it has no database it's just static html
and it's absolutely the best kind of um
side project
it's cheap to host and it can't break i
don't have to worry about server backups
and
um unix systems administration all of
that
all of the data comes from somebody
else's api so we're not responsible for
any of that stuff
and we're not responsible for any user
data either so there is basically
nothing that can go wrong with this
which i think makes it the the perfect
side project it's super fun
um like it's it's it's people really
enjoy it
and it's almost no mental overhead at
all on us
um but i did end up
working on a new kite for me a sort of
new kind of side project
which is the thing that's that's
beginning to take over
my career now so um about so almost
exactly three years ago um when i was
still at eventbrite
i started this project called dataset
which is an open source project
to help people explore analyze and
publish their data
and the inspiration for this was some
work that they'd back at the guardian
um when i first joined the guardian um
one of the people i met there was a
reporter called simon rodgers who was
the
guardian's sort of data nerd reporter he
sat in the newsroom
and he had a hard drive full of excel
spreadsheets and anytime somebody wanted
to do a visualization an infographic
simon rodgers was the person they'd ask
for the data and he
he could get your data on absolutely
anything he was like
phoning up russian cultural departments
and and arguing them over the phone and
trying to get them to email him things
and so on he was absolutely amazing at
it
um and so i said to him you've got all
of these spreadsheets
what happens to them he goes oh i've got
them archived on my hard drive and so he
had a hard drive with
hundreds and hundreds of immaculate
excel spreadsheets of data around the
world
and so we started brainstorming how we
could publish this stuff like what more
can we do with this
we started a thing called the guardian
data blog where basically
we published things in google sheets so
a story we got the newspaper which
was with an infographic and then we put
a post up on the guardian data blog with
a google sheet
that had all of that broad data in it
and we built up a
this worked really well we had a a
flicker group
of um to databases people
who would take data from the guardians
data blog and visualize it and remix it
and so forth
it was fantastic um the one frustration
i had with it is
i felt like there should be a better way
than google sheets of publishing this
data
right if you're publishing data to the
world is google sheets really the
sort of state of the art in data sharing
um
and so the idea behind data set is to
address
the unit originally to address exactly
that problem and
actually i'll switch to a demo because
that's the easiest way to show you what
this kind of
what this thing looks like so dataset is
a web application for exploring data
plus a bunch of tools for for deploying
these web applications online
and this is a data set of global power
plants by the world resource institute
it's thirty three thousand rivals
and i mean it's a table of data so
you've got a country in the name and the
capacity and latitude and longitude but
dataset adds a bunch of extra stuff on
top of it it adds
um there's a feature called facets which
is
essentially pivot tables or group by
accounts and sql
where it can say okay there are 8 000 um
power plants in the united states 4 000
in china
the primary fuel is solar hydro wind
that kind of thing
and but it also does um it also has a
plug-in mechanism that lets you add
visualizations
so here i've just clicked load all i'm
loading all 33 000 power plants in the
world onto this map
um which instantly starts showing you
interesting things like
um there are two power plants in
antarctica for example
um let's let's see what those are
um here we go um so mcmurdo station
has a oil powered generator
and they've also um got a wind generator
down there
um owned by meridian energy which is
kind of interest
thing um but you've also with the facets
you can do things like
um say you know what just show me the
new the 198 nuclear power plants in the
world
of which 61 in the united states 90 new
in france
let's click on france now i'm seeing the
nuclear power plants that exist in
france um
and if i want to do more stuff with that
i can export it so anything you can see
in here you can get after csv this is a
csv file of nuclear power plants in
france i can get it out as a json if i
want to do
visualization work against it um so the
core
initial idea here was given any shape of
data set
if you can get it into like relational
database tables
stick it in a sqlite database because
those are very cheap and inexpensive to
run
you can you can then deploy it online
and other people can
you can explore it other people can
explore it and they can start building
integrations against it
um and this
turned out to be absolutely the perfect
project for me
because i love side projects and having
a
side project which itself kicks out more
side projects like
i can do global power plants one day and
um
little weird museums the next day and uh
foreign agent registration lobbyists and
all of these different things
um it's it's it's it's
pretty much everything that i it takes
all of the boxes and keeping me engaged
and interested
um and so i worked on this as an open
source project for a year and a half
um and then i heard about this
opportunity at stanford university where
they have a fellowship program
for journalists so it's called jsk
fellowships and the idea is they get a
bunch of journalists from around the
world they pay them
to spend a year at stanford thinking
about interesting problems and
uh kind of to be honest it was there's
an aspect of it it's also helping like
journalists not get too burned out and
so forth um
and somebody said you know what this
project here is exactly the kind of
thing they'd be interested in
so i applied for that and got in and
spent got to spend
a full year a full academic year at
stanford
being essentially paid to think about
stuff
and tinker on things that i thought were
interesting which on the one hand was
absolutely amazing
on the other hand i think it's ruined me
because that fellowship ended a few
months ago
and i have no desire to go and get a
full-time job working on
anything other than things that i find
interesting
um yeah there's a there's a
there's me sat in the corner with a
bunch of ludicrously talented
journalists from around the world
super exciting i learned i learned a
huge amount there um
and so a few of the lessons i've learned
from from dataset um so dataset is
aggressively
open source um and i did that mainly
because
i've run a startup and it's sold and
it's shut down and
i know full well that the trajectory of
most
startups and most projects is to
eventually peter out but i'm building
software for journalists right if i want
newsrooms around the world to use my
software
i do not want to then have that software
become unavailable to them you know the
news industry is in enough trouble
already without me um
without me causing more problems by you
know yanking the rug out from underneath
them
so from the start i wanted it to be um
open source
and one of the things that i found has
worked incredibly well for this
is i have a plug-in system for it which
was
mainly inspired by wordpress you know
with wordpress you've got
a decent cms with 7 000 plugins that
mean it can solve any publishing problem
in the world
um and i'm k so i figured if i can get
the same kind of thing going for my
project
and all of these visualizations and
features that i never even have dreamed
of other people can start contributing
so data set supports plugins there are
about 50 plugins at the moment i wrote
all the three of them but that's okay
you know writing plugins your own system
is a great way to
to make sure that it's working um this
is the new data set website which i
launched actually just last week which
has a plugins directory where you can
see
like i've got the the map i showed you
earlier is a plug-in that visualizes
latitude and longitude data
i've got a graphql plugin and code
search and charts and
all sorts of bits and pieces and this
plug-in thing has been
so incredibly liberating for me because
the joy of plugins
is i have a crazy idea for a feature
normally you wouldn't add that to your
project because there's that risk that
the feature if it turns out it's a bad
idea
your your project gets craftier and
crafty and crafty and eventually it
collapses
but with plugins the risk of ad of
trying out a new feature falls to almost
zero so as an example um
i love you i love sql um i was very
skeptical about graphql
and so i built a graphql plugin for
dataset to prove that graphql was a dumb
idea
like it was and um actually it had the
opposite effect i really liked it and
now i'm much more on the graphql train
than i used to be
but the fact that i have this plugin
system meant i could try out something
which i thought was
actively gonna be a bad idea but i could
still invest in it and experiment with
it
put it out there iterating independently
of core um
and that's been brilliant and like like
um
just yesterday somebody released a
plug-in that adds a new charting feature
to data set
which and because it's um because it's a
plug-in based
they don't even have to file a pull
request and have me review their code
like literally i woke up in the morning
and my software had gained features
which is i mean that's the dream right
if if you don't have to do any work at
all and somebody makes your project
better
i don't see how it gets any any cooler
than that
um and what this what the thing that
really excites me about this project
is i said earlier with lanyards we
didn't think that this was our 10-year
project
with data set i think it is like i'm
enjoying it today
even more than i was when i started it
three years ago and i could absolutely
see myself still
still being thrilled to work on this
project in 10 years time
and that's a rare thing like i don't
think opportunities like that come along
very often in careers it's certainly
this is the first time in my career
i've found a project i felt has that
kind of longevity to it
um and you know i'm going to show you a
very quick bonus
um a very quick bonus project
um that i've been building on top of
dataset
this is an idea i started exploring at
stanford where i realized that there was
all of this data about
me in the world all of these like
companies have all of the data about me
and i can get it back out of them a lot
of them have apis a lot of them have
gdpr
exports where you can click a button and
get a zip file of all of your facebook
data and all of your twitter data and so
forth
so i started building a project called
dog sheep where the idea is to gather
all of my personal data
into a private data warehouse running on
top of dataset
that lets me explore it my favorite demo
from dog sheep is
um every time i check in somewhere on
swarm
with my dog cleo i use the wolf emoji in
the swarm check-in message
which means that i can run a data i can
run a sql query
where i look for things where the the
check-in message contains the wolf emoji
which because it's got last student
longitude it gets visualized on a map so
this is my
dog's personal map of her favorite
places
based on her swarm check-ins which is
clearly a
that is a killer app that's something
that's that's very worth spending
spending a lot of engineering time
figuring out um and if you're interested
in that
i gave a talk at um the github speaker
series
a few weeks ago about this called
personal data warehouses which goes into
a full demo
of um of all of the other ludicrous
things i've been able to do with this i
have a copy of my genome that i can
query
using sql now which is is super exciting
um but yeah jumping back um so the
challenge i have right now is i found my
10-year project
i need to do it sustainably right at the
moment i'm not making any money at all
because
i don't want to have a job because i'm
having too much fun and so i've started
spinning i've got to consult
some consulting gigs at the moment
around this um and i'm also
i'm most of the way through building out
ace a sort of
hosted version of this the sas version
because
one of the problems i found with this um
with open source software is i'm
building tools for journalists
but if they have to like install it on
their computer and figure out a python
development environment
and then work out where to host it
somewhere it's just not going to happen
it's unreasonable to ask people to
to self-host this kind of software um
so i'm starting to figure out how i'm
going to do the sort of pay me pay me
per month for your team's
in dataset instance um but yeah that's a
sort of lightning tour of
uh of my of my my sort of story so far
and like i said really the um the thing
i realized is
it was the side projects that led to
basically
everything every opportunity i've had
along the way
started out as some kind of side project
that i was tinkering on and then if i
was lucky that turned into a great
opportunity and if i was unlucky it
would
it turned into sort of a tragic um like
backup failure
but uh but you know you you learn stuff
from every single one of these
um but yeah so that's that's where i am
right now i'd love to
love to take questions and just have a
conversation about some of some of these
themes
hi simon my name is xander my internet
connection is a bit
poor here so i hope i don't cut out um
i hope this question isn't presumptive
uh but
do you play dungeons and dragons i
haven't done in a very long time okay
thanks i was just curious so here's a
more substantive question
uh what did you learn about graphical
graphql from your experiment that
changed your mind about it
uh you actually you you you misspoke and
gave
gay gave the reason it's it's graphical
it's the so the thing with graphql
is that um it includes this incredibly
powerful
like interactive um api explorer which
oh hold on that's the wrong one
let's do github two sql like graphql
um so graph so graphical is this
interface here
and it's got amazing autocomplete like i
can type
um here we go apparently i can get back
the email field
which is blank but yeah it's um
it's absolutely superb right the um as
an interface for mucking around with
apis this this is just so good
and so yeah for me this was the killer
feature the fact that
i can start with a relational database
the plug-in that i've built
uses for it figures out foreign key
relationships to have nested fields and
all of that kind of stuff
and it means that with i install this
one plug-in and suddenly i've got
full um like full auto complete uh
access to my entire data model which
i i love that um and also the um
graphql is so good at doing the nested
thing the fact that i can say
give me back my repositories for each
repository give me
the five most recent issues for each
issue give me the name of the
the name of the person who filed it all
of that it's it's awesome
so yeah for but the other thing is that
um one of the reasons i was skeptical of
graphql is that
at eventbrite our front-end developers
kept on saying we should use graphql
and i was part of the back-end team on
the architecture team and we're looking
at that thinking
how are we going to do that without you
completely crashing the website you're
going to
spark off 500 sql queries with every
feature that you build it's going to be
a disaster
um but data set is built on top of
this database called database called
sqlite
and the one thing that sqlite is
particularly good at is
handling 500 queries at once because
with like my sequel of postgres each
query is a round trip to a server
somewhere
with sqlite it's a c function call to a
local file on disk
so something that triggers 500 queries
in sql lite is like calling 500
functions it's fine
um but yeah so uh i just
i got hooked on it because because of
graphical essentially
thanks
do we have more questions for simon
hey simon i have a question uh
so you definitely build a lot of
fascinating site projects and
i'm curious on how do you uh
when you when you finish building
something how do you promote it is it
usually to your friends or
do you put it up on some forums so it's
discoverable by
by the mass number of mass websites
i wonder how do you go about it so one
joy of side projects
is i don't feel the pressure to promote
them too widely you know if like owls
near me
honestly if i find it amusing and if i
occasionally show it to somebody on my
phone that's completely fine
but at the same time i've got 20 or
thousand followers on twitter so i
promote stuff on twitter
um and that that that's great and then
for the technical stuff like on datasets
uh
mainly i go for things like hack and use
um like i've got
quite a good track record of getting
onto the hack and use home page with
some of these things
and that drives an absurd amount of
traffic um
so yeah if it's so um when we were
running lanyard i did a lot of promotion
of it on quora and places like that so i
feel like
subreddits are really good for depending
on on on the project
um and then i finally a month ago i
finally started an email newsletter
because
that's clearly like a massive wasted
opportunity if you're not if you're not
doing that
if you've got a topic that that people
might want to subscribe to so i have a
thing called the
um the dataset weekly newsletter which i
do not send out weekly um it's
normally two two or three times a month
but this is um
this is where i'm starting to build up
that mailing list the moment i started
doing this i've been kicking myself
because
you actually get people's email
addresses like for the first time in
three years
i have actual contact details for people
who care about the thing that i'm
building
um by kicking myself for not having
started doing that much much earlier
got it that's great thank you
simon uh thank you very much for your
work on django i am a
huge fan and i i use it for all my
projects
so thank you for planting that seed all
those years ago
um are you curious how
you are exploring the different paths
to some kind of funding
slash revenue stream i'm curious about
that too
um i'm definitely still figuring out if
there's anyone in the call who's
successfully commercialized an open
source project i'd love to talk to you
i mean i'm starting to pick pick up some
consulting things which work
it feels like the sas thing would be the
most likely to become sustainable over
time because you know once you've got
monthly recurring revenue and you can
keep on growing that that's that's
it feels like many of the open source
businesses that i really respect that's
one of the things that worked for them
and i am getting i'm getting inbound
interest from some investors which is
always a great position to be in um
we've i've done a funded startup before
lanyard we've raised 1.4 million dollars
and there's a lot of stress you know
where if you raise 1.4 million dollars
your
your time no longer entirely belongs to
you so
what i'm thinking i want to do with this
one is i'd much rather bootstrap it to a
point where it's
essentially where it's you know
sustainable for me to make a decent
income
and then i feel like once you've
bootstrapped it if you do want to expand
it and raise money
you raise money in much better terms
because you don't you know you don't
need
their money to keep on going um so there
is a potential world in which
i bootstrap up to being sustainable and
that and then
raise money from investors um i'm just
i'm i'm has and partly you know it's ugh
this has not been a great year for
making long-term plans you know
um yeah that's what i'm thinking about
at the moment
i got and you think journalists
journalists are going to be your
kind of focal market given your
background i mean no because they
haven't got any money
um my well my feeling around journalists
is
so data journalism is a really
interesting speciality
and um i go to this uh data this
conference called nikah the
um computer-assisted reporting
conference because that's what they
called it
back in the 70s when they started using
mainframes to help with reporting
stories
um and they're an amazing bunch and i
think there is enough money
in like newsrooms to to at least start
the ball rolling
but the real theory i have is if i can
build software that helps
journalists break stories that those
features for corporate strategy
departments and think tanks and analysts
uh
they all have to solve the same kinds of
problems so it feels like i've got
an initial niche audience who are
who would be amazing to to get the to
get the ball rolling and make sure i've
got the right kind of feature set
but aren't going to make me a huge
amount of money but tools that work for
them should work for the people who do
have
the money that's my theory anyway yeah i
mean
if i think about what you just showed
with data set i mean i i don't know the
inside details of palantir but it
doesn't seem
too far off the kind of platform that
they have well this is the thing it's
like
there are there's lots of activity
around big data
right there are loads of companies
talenteer and snowflake and all of these
companies who are like you've got
terabytes of whatever
we will help you solve solve problems on
top of it
but meanwhile nobody seems to be
targeting small data and my definition
of small data these days is data that
won't fit on my
phone and i think this phone's got a
terabyte of space on it now or it's like
half a terabyte so
small data is still pretty something
huge
in journalism um the interesting data
sets you look at tend to be 100
megabytes so
like i've got one i'm looking at mine
that's three gig and three gigabytes
works completely fine on a laptop or on
cheap hosting
um so part of what i'm thinking about is
okay what are the opportunities in this
sort of small at the smaller end of data
most companies to be honest only have in
the order of gigabytes of data that they
actually want to analyze
you know you might have terabytes of log
files somewhere but for the most part
and at eventbrite we had a data
warehouse team and a giant expensive
data warehouse costing tens of thousands
of dollars a month
and i was still using dataset to solve
certain problems where
i'd suck down a couple of thousand
records that i needed to
investigate more closely get them a date
up my laptop and start digging through
them
that was one of the the points at which
i realized that this thing was was
genuinely useful beyond
just mucking around with publishing
power plant data or whatever
um and the um likewise the the personal
data warehouse stuff you
do not need um your own copy of palantir
for your tweets and your emails and so
forth
but does that like everyone i show the
um
full demo to it's like no this is
clearly a valuable thing this is useful
to me
um so yeah so i i'm i'm i'm really
interested in exploring that sort of
the what you can do with small data oh
the other
great example these days is airtable
airtable is a phenomenal product
and that is not for terabytes of data
like airtable is for
um actually somebody pointed out to me
recently that airtable is for data that
you can manually enter
right you're not going to pull in
gigabytes of log files into an air table
but if you've got a team who need to
maintain their own sort of inbuilt um
home-built crm or whatever
airtable's absolutely perfect and
there's a possible world where
dataset evolves into the open source
alternative to airtable
but there are also about half a dozen
other possible worlds the dataset might
evolve into so i'm still
still trying to figure out which
direction i should focus it in
that makes sense thank you
it's actually genuinely one of the
hardest problems i have for this project
is explaining what the hell it is
because you can
dataset it's a swiss army knife you can
do so much stuff with it
um my latest attempt is i've got a page
on the dataset website of use cases
where i'm going to add i deliberately
get around about a 20
just to try and get across the message
that this does a lot this can be used to
do a lot of different stuff
i mean i think the key things are
exploitative data analysis instant data
publishing and rapid prototyping
but i use it for like digital forensics
i use it
um i've used it for security um
responding to security instance
um i build the dataset website is
dataset it's just with a custom theme
and template so it doesn't look like it
one of my other side projects
is a website to help um where i post
reviews of
tiny museums that i've been to um so
things like uh and the new orleans
historic voodoo museum and so on um
before the pandemic
this was a great hobby because any town
you go to there's going to be a weird
little museum somewhere
that's about pharmacies or voodoo or
whatever it is
and so i've been trying to build build
up a and build
essentially building a database of weird
museums i've been to um and again this
is this is data set but it's with a
custom theme
it's got a use my location button so
it's weird museums near you
i'm 0.16 miles away from the comic rock
stars toilet seat museum
has anyone seen this this is if you're
in san francisco
okay so in hayes valley in there's a
comic book store called isotope
and this is the the guy who runs isotope
and he collects
um toilet seats that have been
illustrated by famous comic book artists
like
they come to his store and he gives them
a toilet seat and they illustrate it and
he's got like
over a hundred of these things now and
it's like a
that's like warren ellis and people like
that have illustrated his toilet seats
and if you go in there or today if you
go to the window and look in you can see
this amazing collection um and that to
me
this is this is this is what life is
about right it's finding
finding the people who collect the
toilet seats with the illustrations on
them so yeah but niche museums here
is just it's um it's data set uh if you
go to slash browse
here's my database table of museums and
on a map
um and yeah the um and then the the home
page is a custom template that adds
images and and all of that kind of stuff
but yeah so dataset does that too um
which means that
i don't have the i definitely don't have
the the right elevator pitch for it yet
if you
give me 15 minutes i can explain the
project to you but that's not really uh
it's not really a great way of
explaining what something does it's
challenging as well because
it comes down to oh what's that
marketing term um
it's pinning or framing or something
that thing where if i say that dataset
is a data warehouse
it will be compared to hive and
snowflake and
and so on if i say that it is like
airtable
or or a personal database it will be
compared to a table and access and excel
and at the moment somebody starts
comparing one of those tools they get a
fixed idea of what it can do
what kind of money they should be
spending on it all of that so it's
tricky
um but you know i the more conversations
i have about it the better i get it
the closer i get to figuring out how to
explain it to people i think
and that was incredible i uh i have a
question which is like a bit of a meta
question
i which is uh how do you perform and and
and like how do you go about not
specifically daily basis like for
example
that for like a feature and how do you
keep fresh
like you know stay at it fresh but also
be able to bring some to build that out
all the way through
so partly the big cheat that i have
is i basically only work on projects
where i know that it's going to be
really easy to build
i know it's going to be quick so i've
spent basically i've spent the last
20 years hoarding little like cheat
sheet
little tricks that i can use and then
once every now and then
something come along and i think you
know what because i've built this in the
past and because of this and because of
that
this is a project that will take me take
me a couple of days and i can launch it
and honestly i don't work on projects
that take more than a week before i can
put
something out there most of the plugins
i write or a couple of hours and then i
stick out the initial release
and that's something i learned um i mean
that's it's the release early release
often thing it turns out
that's so important for side projects
because the alternative
is that you never ship your side
projects and wildlife near you
the thing that we built in a fort um we
worked on it for
for a week together on this fortress and
then we took it home with just a few
more details to to finish off
and 12 months later we finally shipped
it
because it was just like oh it'll be
perfect if we just add this one
integration with flickr and if we just
do this and just do this and just do
this
and of course we launched it and
instantly everyone ignored most of the
features we built and they cared about
this one little thing that we didn't
know was important
so the the thing i learned from that is
yeah
your product isn't i i uh a side project
almost isn't the side project
until either other people can see it or
at least you're actively using it
yourself
um and so yeah that's something i'm i'm
very
very passionate like uh i've got this um
personal home page
on github where you know github have
this personal readme thing
and so i built a personal readme which
is self updating it has a github action
which runs a couple of times an hour and
pulls some feeds and
and and um puts them in there but my
favorite bit of this
is this these are the releases that i'm
making to my project
so this is every time i tag something as
the release version and push it out to
the python package index or whatever
and then most days i have at least one
release of something
because because i'm trying to release
early and release often
um and so i will i will add a a bug fix
and i'll ship a bug
fix release and that's that's you know
that's done and that's out there
um so yeah that releasing early using
often
going after the projects that are really
easy um here's a really fun example uh
this is something i put out a couple of
weeks ago this is a code search engine
um that does a regular expression code
search
against all of my projects which is a
ridiculously ambitious thing to build
except in this case it took the best
part of a day
because it's running this this open
source tool called rip grep which is
amazing
and this is about about 100 lines of
python code
adding a simple web and face on top of
rip grab
so it take it takes this this really
like ambitious idea for a thing and
turns it into a very quick
turn it turn around in a few hours i've
made a few enhancements to it since then
but um it's a huge cheat right this is
this is this project exists solely
because i was like holy
rip grep has a json export which means
that i can plug it into this thing and
write some code which means i can build
a code search engine
if it was going to take longer than a
few hours i wouldn't have done it um
actually that's a philosophy i have
around data set itself
is i think there's something really
interesting about
tools or technologies that take the
amount of effort required to do
something down
from i'm like even if you've got
something to take a week
like public if you're a newspaper and
you want to publish data about the local
nursing homes
and you need to have an engineer work on
that for a week to get up a web
interface with with like
json export and stuff you're not going
to do that you cannot afford
a week of engineering time for that but
if data set drives drops that down to a
couple of hours
then you will do it so there's this sort
of activation energy where
there are tools and techniques that take
something which is
going to take long enough that you're
not going to select that as a thing to
do and drop it down below the bar
and then and then let you do it and i
love that kind of thing like that to me
is
if you built if if i can build a tool
that means i can do a dozen more
projects in the future
that i wouldn't have done otherwise
because they'd have taken too long
that's that's
that's enormously valuable and again the
data set plug-ins play into all of that
everything i'm building around here is
about
trying to put the least amount of effort
into the most amount of
of sort of value and and stuff that i
can do with it
incredible thank you that was rich
thanks
well it looks like we're at time uh
thank you simon so much for speaking
with us today that was super interesting
and
um please come back and talk with us
again
i'd i mean especially if anyone's got
any insight into how i can
well it's not just um it's not just like
commercializing open source
it's just straight up figuring out how
to do how to set up decent contracting
and consulting gigs that support this
kind of thing as well i'd love to
to swap swap um to swap notes with
people on how to do that
definitely why don't you um could you do
you mind if people contact you
oh absolutely no plea please feel free
to reach out for me
uh reach out me okay great maybe you can
put your email address in the um chat
box
um okay so i'm just williston
um oh
and i'm on twitter as well
there we go
on i think you're muted
thank you um yeah my internet's
principality today but
thank you so much again um i'll save
that email address and
i'll post it maybe in slack um everyone
can access it
thank you again and we thanks for having
me
it was great meeting you all thank you
thanks simon thank you you